Hello everyone I'm
Dr. Eugene Petko from
the Department of
Biomedical Sciences and
today is my pleasure
to welcome all of you
to the cardiac valve
pathology lecture.
Please note that unless
mentioned otherwise
all the images and
information included in
this presentation are
from Robins and Cotran
Pathologic Basis of
Disease the 10th edition.
Please contact me if you have
any additional questions.
On this slide you
have mentioned
all the session objectives.
In brief, at the end of
today's lecture you will be
able to discuss the most
important elements of cardiac
valve pathology. You will
acquire a good understanding
related to etiopathogenesis
and morphological changes
seen in aortic valve stenosis,
mitral valve prolapse,
and mitral annular
calcification.
You will be able to
describe pathological
features seen in acute
rheumatic fever and
rheumatic heart disease,
as well as in infective
endocarditis, non
-bacterial thrombotic
endocarditis, and Liebman
Sachs endocarditis.
Before anything else, I
would like to highlight the
most important features of
valvular disease in general.
Valvular disease might present
as valvular stenosis or
insufficiency. Some patients
might present with both
vulvular stenosis or
insufficiency in the same valve.
Vulvular stenosis it
represents failure of a valve
to open completely obstructing
forward blood flow.
It is determined by a
primary cuspal pathological
process such as calcification
or valve scaring.
Valvular insufficiency
represents failure
of a valve to close
completely As a result,
there is regurgitation
or backflow of blood
This is determined by
a disease of the valve
cusps such as endocarditis
or a destruction
of the valvular
supporting apparatus the
tendinous cords and
the papillary muscle.
Some patients might
present with valvular
pathology in one valve
or in several valves.
Anyway, the most
commonly affected
valve is the mitral valve.
Usually, these patients
will present with a
murmur, which is determined
by a turbulent flow
through the diseased
valve. However, if the
stenosis is severe,
thrills might be palpated.
The outcome. The outcome
in these patients
depends on the valve
or the valves affected,
the degree of impairment and
the tempo of its development.
In addition, the
outcome is determined by
compensatory mechanisms.
For example, cardiac
failure might
develop after a rapid
destruction of aortic
valve by an infection.
By contrast,
rheumatic mitral stenosis
develops very slowly.
In these cases, clinical
effects are well tolerated
until late in the
evolution of the disease.
Now let's summarize the
most important aspects
related to the etiology
of cardiac valvulopathies.
There are two types
of valvulopathies,
congenital and acquired.
The most common
congenital valvulopathy is
the bicuspid aortic
valve stenosis and the
most common acquired
valvulopathies are
represented by aortic
and mitral stenosis.
These pathological
conditions represent
two-thirds of all
valvulopathies.
As mentioned in the right
-side table, the most
important cause of both
mitral and aortic stenosis
is represented by
rheumatic heart disease.
At this stage, we will
not cover the less common
conditions related to mitral
and aortic regurgitation
except mitral valve
prolapse and mitral annular
calcification or
calcification of mitral ring.
However,
all these entities are
enumerated in this table.
Calcific aortic stenosis
Calcific aortic
stenosis is the most
common cause of
aortic stenosis.
It may be asymptomatic
and is seen
incidentally during
routine chest X-ray.
However, some patients
present with severe
symptomatology and
require surgical therapy.
In subjects with normal
valves, it manifests
around 78 years of
age, while in those
with congenital
bicuspid valves is
diagnosed earlier, around
40-50 years of age.
Pathogenesis.
Although simple
progressive age-associated
wear and tear
mechanism is usually
the explanation
for this condition,
cuspal fibrosis and
calcification, which are observed
in aortic stenosis,
could be regarded as the
valvular equivalent of age
-related atherosclerosis.
Therefore atherosclerosis
risk factors
such as hyperlipidemia,
hypertension
and chronic inflammation
are also regarded
as risk factors for
calcific aortic stenosis.
On the right upper side
of this slide we have
several examples of
calcific aortic stenosis.
In image A,
we have a case of
calcific aortic
stenosis in a
previously normal valve.
In this setting, there are
numerous nodular masses
of calcium accumulating
over a long period of time.
In image B, we have numerous
calcific masses developed
on a congenitally bicuspid
valve. there is partial
fusion at the center of
this valve called a raffi.
I would like to highlight
that in both cases
these calcific nodules
protrude into the sinuses of
valsava and mechanically
impair valve opening.
In image C, there is an
extreme case of calcific
aortic stenosis characterized
by fused commissures.
This is seen in some patients
with rheumatic heart disease.
Bicuspid aortic valve.
Congenital bicuspid
aortic valve represents
approximately 50
% of cases of aortic
stenosis in adults.
This is equivalent with
1% of the population.
Some studies have
indicated an increased
number of patients
with congenital aortic
stenosis in some families
It seems that these
individuals have a
mutation of a NOTCH1 gene
As you can see very well
on the left side drawing
The most important
morphological anomaly in
this condition is
represented by two conjointed
cusps forming a larger
valve with a midline raffae
The raffi represents
an area where
calcification begins and
results from incomplete
separation during
natural development
The top right side image
shows a heavily calcified
congenital bicuspid valve
with an associated thrombus
Calcific aortic stenosis
histology On this
slide, we have an image
showing a standard
hematoxilineosin state
section, which was performed
through a heavily
calcified aortic valve.
You can see the calcium
deposits appearing as empty
spaces as calcium was removed
during tissue processing.
Anyway, it is believed
that calcification
begins at the base
of the aortic valve.
Eventually, this abnormal
process will lead to
a reduction in the actual
valve functional area.
This reduction is
associated with an outflow
obstruction and pressure
overload as the heart will
have to push blood against
an increased pressure.
Aortic stenosis
physiopathology.
As mentioned before,
calcific aortic stenosis
may be age-related or
senile, or it may develop
on a bicuspid valve.
This calcified valve will
determine obstruction and
narrowing of the aorta.
This will lead to an
increased pressure
gradient, which in
turn will be associated
with an increased left
ventricular pressure.
In time,
these patients will
develop cardiac
hypertrophy and
cardiac failure.
Patients with
cardiac hypertrophy
will subsequently present with
events such as
angina and syncope.
All of these features
indicate cardiac ischemia and
a severe decreased
compensatory cardiac function.
Prolapse In this
setting, one or both
mitral leaflets are
floppy and prolapse
back into the atrium
during systole.
Mitral valve prolapse
is associated with
conditions characterized
by connective
tissue pathology, such
as Marfan syndrome,
Ehlers-Danlos syndrome,
as well as polycystic
kidney disease and
fragile X syndrome.
Ethiology.
Mitral valve prolapse
is determined
by myxomatous degeneration,
which represents
the deposition of
abnormal material
in the valves.
This can be spontaneous
or primary or secondary to
a connective tissue
disorder. It is also seen in
rheumatic fever and after
myocardial infarction.
Pathogenesis.
In myxomatoid degeneration
of mitral valve,
the leaflets show an
excessive degradation of
collagen and elastin
by proteolytic enzymes.
There is also a significant
accumulation of
abnormal proteoglycans.
As a result of all
these, the corded
tendinale will have an abnormal
plasticity, they become
weak and elongated
In addition, there is
also annular dilatation
of the mitral valve
On the other hand,
in connective tissue disorders,
there is deficiency
of normal collagen as
well as a low level
of velocity And the
leaflets are becoming
thin and translucent
Let's describe the
morphological changes associated
with mitral valve
prolapse As you can see
in this macroscopic
image on the left side of
this slide The mitral
valve will prolapse back
into the left atrium
during cardiac contraction
In some cases, the patient
might develop
atrial dilatation.
This is determined by
valvular insufficiency,
which develops late in
the course of the disease.
The right side image
represents two histological
images, a normal
cardiac valve and a
section taken from a
myxomatous mitral valve.
In the diseased structure,
you can see that its
architecture is severely
disorganized with loosely disposed
collagen in the fibrosa
layer There is also abnormal
proteoglycan in spongiosa
layer of the mitral valve
I would also like to discuss
very briefly the mitral
annular classification,
a condition seen in
patients with myxomatous
degeneration of the mitral
valve but most of the time
an incidental finding.
Usually these patients are
women over 60 years of age
with mitral var prolapse or
any other cardiac pathology
associated with increased
left ventricular pressure.
Pathogenesis.
As you may see in this
image, this condition is
characterized by numerous
irregular hard nodules
representing degenerative
calcific deposits at the base
of the leaflets sometimes
this might be ulcerated
mitral annular
calcification most of
the time requires
no specific therapy
however the
associated conditions
such as mitral valve prolapse
stenosis and or
regurgitation as well as the
conditions which lead
to increased left
ventricular pressure must
be treated specifically.
Also, it is
believed that mitral
annular classification
is associated with
atherosclerotic
disease. Therefore,
the presence of mitral
annular classification should
heighten clinical concern
for concomitant coronary
or antherosclerotic disease
and serve as an opportunity
to address potentially
modifiable cardiovascular
risk factors such as
hypertension and dyslipidemia.
Acid rheumatic fever and
rheumatic heart disease.
Acid rheumatic fever is
immunologically mediated
and represents a multi
-system disease which
affects not only the heart
but also other organs.
Acid rheumatic fever has
an inflammatory character
and develops after pharyngitis
or a skin infection
caused by a group A beta
-hemolytic streptococcus.
Rheumatic heart disease
represents the cardiac
pathology associated with
acute rheumatic fever.
The most important
clinical features are
determined by fibrotic
mitral stenosis.
In fact, rheumatic
heart disease is the
only cause of acquired
mitral stenosis.
Rheumatic fever pathogenesis.
As I mentioned before,
icodraumatic fever
is an immunological
reaction determined
by an infection with
group A beta-hemolytic
streptococcus.
There is a 2-3 weeks
delay in the onset
of clinical features
as the immunological
reaction requires
times for development.
As you can see in this
drawing, the streptococci
have an antigen represented
by the M protein.
The streptococci will
activate beta lymphocytes to
manufacture antibodies
capable of recognizing the
M protein antigen. In
addition, CD4T lymphocytes
are also directed against
streptococcal M protein.
Basically, this
is how the organ
fights against the
bacterial infection.
However,
antibody antigen binding
activates the complement.
This activation
is associated with
recruitment of neutrophils
and macrophages,
further stimulation
of T-cell lymphocytes
leading to cytokine
production, and further
macrophage activation
and tissue damage.
As you can see in this
drawing, all of these would
lead to damage to the
mitral and aortic valves,
arthritis,
and skin involvement.
I would like to highlight
that antibodies and CD4
lymphocytes directed
against streptococcal
M protein recognize
cardiac proteins,
cardiac self-antigens
promoting tissue destruction.
Please note that in
established cases of rheumatic
heart disease, the
streptococci are not seen in
the lesion, as this is an
immunological reaction.
However, as only a
minority estimated at 3%
of patients infected with
group A beta-hemolytic
streptococci develop
acudriomatic fever,
it is likely that the genetic
susceptibility modulates
the development of this
immunological reaction.
I'd like to summarize the
most important clinical
features seen in acudriomatic
fever. As mentioned before,
I could rheumatic fever is
describing a minority of
patients after group A beta
-hemolytic streptococcal
infection and most of
the patients are children
aged between 5 and 15 years
of age. There are five
major diagnostic criteria
joint pain, acute carditis,
nodules,
erythema marginatum
and Sideham chorea.
Let's describe each of
these categories separately.
Acute carditis is
suggested by pericardial
friction rubs and various
types of arrhythmias.
There is myocarditis which
may be seen in some patients
causing cardiac dilatation.
This could culminate
in functional mitral
valve insufficiency
or even heart failure.
About 1% of affected
individuals will
die of fulminant
involvement of the heart
Regarding the joint pain,
this is caused by a migratory
porial arthritis In which
the patient is febrile and
one large joint is affected
after another The joint
becomes painful and swollen
for several days But then
the condition subsides,
leaving no residual disability
On this slide, you see
the typical aspect of
a subcutaneous nodule
associated with an
acridriumatic fever.
These nodules are located
on the extensor surfaces
of fingers or arms.
Also on this slide, you have a
classical example of
Veritema marginato.
This is defined by
large irregular skin
rush areas measuring
several centimeters.
In addition, these patients
present with involuntary
rapid dance-like movements
involving all limbs and
the trunk. This is diagnostic
for Sideham chorea.
Now I would like to
discuss very briefly
the most important
morphological changes
associated with
acuidraumatic fever.
Myocarditis.
Myocarditis is
characterized by the
presence of Ashoff's
bodies, which
are pathognomonic
for this condition.
Ashoff's bodies are
associated with a diffuse
inflammation of the
heart and are composed of
lymphocytes, plasma cells,
and anistikov cells.
Anistikov cells are large
activated macrophages.
It should be noted
that Ashoff's bodies
might be seen not only
myocardium but also
in pericardium and
endocardium and are
indicative of inflammation
of these structures.
This image shows an actual body
in a patient with
acute carditis.
The myocardium shows a
nodule composed of various
types of inflammatory
cells. There is also
necrosis which is indicated
here by a long arrow.
Necrosis appears in
hematoxylin eosin stained slide
as a structureless pinkish
material. The small arrow
identify Anishchikov
cells, large
activated macrophages
with prominent nuclei
and chromatin
condensed into long
wavy ribbon-like
pattern, hence the name
of caterpillar cells
used by some authors
when describing the
Anishchikov cells.
On this slide, the
left side image shows a
classical representation
of the microscopic changes
associated with acridromatic
fever endocarditis.
This is characterized
by irregular
small bifermi-adherent
vegetations along
the closure line of
the mitral valve.
These vegetations are
made of fibrin, and
they probably represent
damage caused by opening
and closing of the
inflamed myocardium.
The right side image
shows an example
of acuidraumatic
fever pericarditis.
The surface of this
heart is covered
by a fibrinous
pericardial exudate
with a bread and
butter-like pattern.
Reumatic heart disease
clinical features.
These features are seen
years or even decades
after initial episode
of acridromatic fever.
In addition to cardiac murmurs,
cardiac hypertrophy,
dilatation and heart failure,
these patients present
with arrhythmias such
as atrial fibrillation,
thromboembolic complications
and endocarditis.
The long-term prognosis
variable from one
patient to the other.
However, surgical repair
and replacement of damaged
valves has significantly
improved the outcome
in these patients.
Heart disease morphology.
While the tricuspid and
pulmonary valves are very
uncommonly affected in rheumatic
heart disease, the mitral
valve is always involved.
Two-thirds of cases present
only with mitral valve
stenosis, While in one
third of the patients,
mitral valve stenosis
is associated with a
pathological aortic valve
The morphology in these
patients is represented
by extensive fibrosis and
calcification Resulting
in severe rheumatic mitral
valve stenosis The so
-called fish mouth stenosis,
which is shown in this
image This type of lesion
induces left outer
hypertrophy and dilatation
A dilated atrium
may harbor moral
thrombi that could embolize.
Anyway, left atrial
dilatation and
hypertrophy, which
appears in time,
determine congestion in
the lungs, leading to
right ventricular hypertrophy
and heart failure.
Infective endocarditis.
This pathological entity
represents a microbial
infection of the heart valves of
moral endocardium leading
to formation of vegetations.
These vegetations are made of
thrombotic debris
and microorganisms.
Apart from heart
valves and endocardium,
aorta and other blood
vessels as well as
prosthetic devices
might become infected.
Most infections in this
setting are bacterial
but fungal infections
are also seen.
Traditionally, infective
endocarditis has been
classified on clinical
grounds into acute and
subacute forms based on
severity and tempo and
whether there is underlying
valvular pathology.
Acute infective endocarditis.
This is caused by
an infection of a previously
normal heart valve
by virulent agents such
as taphylococcus aureus.
The lesions are extensive
in these cases and
it is difficult to
manage the patient and
oftentimes, apart from
antibiotic therapy,
they have to undergo surgery.
Moreover, despite
the best therapy,
morbidity and
mortality are high.
In contrast,
subacute infective endocarditis
is induced by organisms
with lower virulence such
as viridans streptococci.
This causes
insidious infections
of previously deformed valves.
However, there is less
valvular destruction.
The disease may last for
many weeks or months,
but it may be cured only
by antibiotic therapy.
Infective endocarditis
risk factors.
is seen in higher
numbers in patients with
rheumatic heart disease,
mitral valve prolapse
and calcific valvular
stenosis, in those with
prosthetic devices,
in various congenital
heart defects,
and in immunocompromised
patients,
especially in those
with immunodeficiency,
drug abuse disorder,
neutropenia,
malignancy, and
diabetes mellitus.
I would like to summarize
the most important
clinical features in
infective endocarditis.
This condition is
characterized by an abrupt
onset of fever, chills
and general weakness.
All of these signs
are non-specific
but fever is the
most consistent sign.
Fever might not be seen in
older adults.
This older patient
may present only with
weight loss and tiredness.
In addition, murmurs are
also noted in infective
endocarditis and are
determined either by a new
valvular defect or pre
-existing valvular condition.
Infective
endocarditis etiology.
In more than 60% of cases,
infective endocarditis
is induced in a native
valve by Streptococcus
viridans, which is normally
seen in oral cavity.
The native valve
in these cases is
previously damaged or
abnormal. In contrast,
Staphylococcus aureus,
which is found on
the skin, promotes
a virulent infection
of healthy or deformed
valves in up to 20
-30% of all infective
endocarditis cases.
Bacterial endocarditis
may also be determined
by enterococci and
the Hasek group.
Hasek is the abbreviation
for hemophilus,
actinobacillus,
cardiobacterium,
acinella, and kingella.
All of these are normally
seen in oral cavity.
Gram-negative bacilli
and fungi might also
be seen in cases of
infective endocarditis.
A special note for prosthetic
valve endocarditis,
this condition is seen
one to two months after
surgery and is caused
by skin flora such as
staphylococcus aureus or
staphylococcus epidermidis.
Prosthetic valve
endocarditis may also be
diagnosed after more than
one year after surgery,
but these cases are
often associated
with streptococcal infections.
Infective endocarditis
morphology. The most important
morphological hallmark
in infective endocarditis
is represented by the
presence of vegetations.
These are friable bulky
and destructive lesions
containing fibrin inflammatory
cells and microorganisms
the aortic and mitral
valves are frequently
involved although the
valves of the right heart
are affected
especially in those
with iv drug abuse disorder
vegetations are
prone to embolization
in various organs
and parts of the body
In this slide, the image
labeled A shows a case of
subacute endocarditis caused
by Streptococcus viridans.
The heart was opened
longitudinally and you
can see numerous variable
large vegetations on
the mitral valve. The
image labeled B represents
a case of acute
endocarditis of a congenital
by cuspid aortic valve.
This was the final
result of a Staphylococcus
aureus infection.
As you can see, indicated
by the tip of the
forceps, the vegetations
are large, friable,
and there is massive
cuspal destruction
as well as a ring
abscess formation.
Infective endocarditis
histology. As mentioned
before, infective
endocarditis is
characterized by the
presence of vegetations.
In this microscopic picture,
we see a small fragment
of tissue which was taken
from a large-sized vegetation.
This lesion is comprised
of fibrin and platelets.
Also, as indicated by
the tip of the arrow,
the superficial layer
of this structure
contains inflammatory
cells and bacteria which
appear darker than the
rest of the lesion.
I would like to discuss
some clinical signs
which are diagnostic for
infective endocarditis.
Janeway's lesions.
These are small erythematous
or hemorrhagic micular
non-tender lesions seen
on palms and soles. They
result from embolization
of friable vegetations.
Small friable fragments
become dislodged and
subsequently end up in
a terminal blood vessel.
Rot spots.
These are oval
retinal hemorrhages
with pale centers
seen in only 2% of
patients with
effective endocarditis.
They result after
embolization of
small fragments of vegetations.
However, some authors
claim that these
lesions might have an
immunological cause.
Nailbed or splinter
hemorrhages.
They also result from
embolization of small
friable fragments of
vegetations which end
up in the small vessels
of the nail bed.
Osler nodes. These are
small tender subcutaneous
nodules that develop in the
pulp of the digits or at
the level of interphalangeal
joints of the fingers.
They can last from
hours to days.
The underlying cause of
these nodules is debatable.
Early reports favored an
allergic or immunological
cause, but more
recent studies have
isolated bacteria from
within the nodules.
Therefore, it is believed
that they result from
embolization of small
vegetation fragments.
Non-bacterial thrombotic
endocarditis. This
condition is characterized
by deposition of small 1
to 5 mm sterile thrombi
on the valvular leaflets.
Frequently, non-bacterial
thrombotic endocarditis
is seen in cancers
such as mucinous
adenocarcinomas. It is also
seen in patients with severe
infections or sepsis
including those with
hypercoagulable states
such as disseminated
intravascular coagulation
and hyperestrogenic states.
In all these clinical
settings the patients
present with normal valves
but endocardial trauma
from an indwelling
catheter is also a risk
factor for non-bacterial
thrombotic endocarditis.
On the left side of this
slide, there are two images.
Image A shows a
longitudinally dissected heart
with a row of thrombotic
vegetations along
the line of closure
of the mitral valve
leaflets. These vegetations
are non destructive
and do not cause an
inflammatory reaction.
However, they can
embolize, causing
infarcts in the brain,
heart and kidneys.
Image B represents the
microscopic structure of a
sterile vegetation,
characteristic for non-bacterial
thrombotic endocarditis.
There is no inflammatory
infiltrate in the valve cuts,
which can be seen in the
left side of this image. The
thrombotic sterile material
is very loosely attached
to the valvular surface.
And this is composed
only of fibrin,
platelets and other
blood components.
Liebman Sachs
endocarditis. This type of
endocarditis is seen in
systemic lupus erythematosus,
which is an
immunological condition.
It is characterized by
small 1 to 4 mm sterile
vegetations. These
vegetations result from immune
complex deposition with
activation of complement.
The vegetations
are seen anywhere
on the valvular surfaces,
on corded tendon, or on
atrial and ventricular septum.
These lesions might
promote fibrosis,
scarring, and fusion of
the valvular leaflets.
The right side image
represents a dissected
heart showing several
pink sterile vegetations
along the line of
closure of mitral valve.
The left side microscopic
image shows a section
of the mitral valve
leaflet vegetation
stained with hematoxylin
eosin. There is
inflammation of the valve
or valvulitis indicated
by the presence of
neutrophils and monocytes.
On the upper right
side of this image,
you might see fibrinoid
necrosis, composed
of fine eosinophilic
acellular material.
No micro-organes are
seen in this lesion.
On the last slide of
today's lecture, there is a
summary which might help
you during your studies.
Initially, we have
described the most salient
features of valvular disease
and then we have discussed
the most important forms
of aortic stenosis,
the calcific aortic stenosis
and the aortic stenosis
which develops in a
congenital bicuspid valve.
Currently it is accepted
that aortic stenosis is
caused by the age-related
wear and tear which is
the equivalent of age
-related atherosclerosis.
Then we have
defined mitral valve
prolapse and mitral
annular calcification.
The first one is
myxomatous degeneration or
deposition in the mitral
valve leaflets of an
abnormal material
reaching proteoglycans.
Mitral annular calcification
on the other side
is abnormal deposition
of calcium in the mitral
fibrous annulus. Then
we have discussed the
acuidraumatic fever versus
rheumatic heart disease.
Acuidraumatic fever
is considered an
immunological reaction
determined by a group
A beta-hemolytic
streptococcal infection.
Most of the time
it's a pharyngitis.
We have presented
the histological
hallmarks of
acuidraumatic fever, the
ash of bodies and
the anistikov cells.
Also, we have defined the
major clinical criteria,
and we have explained in
detail the related carditis.
Also, we have debated the
morphology of rheumatic
heart disease, which was
presented in contrast
with acute rheumatic
fever. It was highlighted
that rheumatic heart
disease is the only cause
of acquired mitral
stenosis. Then, we have
presented the acute and
subacute forms of infective
endocarditis and their
etiological factors.
Histologically,
infective endocarditis is
remarkable by the
presence of large friable
vegetations containing
fibrin and platelets
mixed with inflammatory
cells and bacteria.
In this lecture, we
have also explained the
appearance of infecting
endocarditis clinical
features, such as genoay
lesions, rot spots,
nail bed or splinter
hemorrhages, and Osler nodules.
Also, we have defined the
non-bacterial thrombotic
endocarditis, which
is associated with
cancers, such as mucinous
adenocarcinoma. carcinoma.
It is also seen in
hypercoagulable states.
This condition is
notable for its non
-bacterial, sterile
vegetation, composed only of
fibrin, platelets,
and blood components.
These vegetations are friable
and can easily embolize.
In the end, we
have discussed the
Leibmann-Sax
endocarditis, which is a
feature of systemic
lupus erythematosus.
This is an immunological
condition and
the resulting vegetations
are seen on any
valve surface or
region of endocardium.
In Leibmann-Sax
endocarditis, vegetations
occur as a result
of activation of
complement with imun
complex deposition.
Thank you very much
for your attention
and good luck
with your studies.
Bye-bye.